Guide to the Private Adjudication Center Records, 1982-1992
Duke University. University Archives
Private Adjudication Center records 1982-1992
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University. Private Adjudication Center.
9 linear feet Extent: 6000 Items
The Private Adjudication Center is an independent corporation founded by the Board of Trustees of Duke University and was attached to the School of Law. School of Law Professor Paul Carrington served on the Executive Committee, Board of Directors, from 1983-2003, as Executive Director in 1988, President from 1989-1994, and Chair of Board, 1995-2002. The materials include correspondence between PAC representatives throughout the United States and in various foreign countries as well as minutes, reports, proposals, and other materials. There are a few case files within this collection.
UA.26.03.0001
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
In off-site storage; 48 hours notice required for retrieval.
Provenance
The Private Adjudication Center Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1991, 1993.
Historical Note
On November 4, 1983, the formation of the Private Adjudication Center was authorized by the Executive Committee of the Board of Trustees of Duke University as an independent, non-profit corporation. Its purpose was to promote research and development in the field of Alternative Dispute Resolution. As recently as 2002, PAC provided education, services, and empirical research in dispute management and resolution to clients across the United States. Duke PAC performed ground-breaking work in the administration of mass tort actions and provided a range of conflict resolution services.
Once affiliated with the School of Law, the Private Adjudication Center ceased to be a working center at Duke University as recently as 2002-2003.
Collection Overview
Collection contains the charter and by-laws of PAC, correspondence, memoranda, annual reports, responses to requests for proposals for dispute resolution, informational books and brochures, grant applications, minutes of the PAC Board and other records concerning the establishment, promotion, funding, and operation of the Center. Also included is material concerning other dispute resolution centers, the National Institute for Dispute Resolution, the legal status of arbitration, and the relation of resolution centers to the courts. Material ranges in date from 1982-1992.
Subject Headings
Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University. School of Law. Private Adjudication Center; National Dispute Resolution Center (U.S.)
Related Material
Terry Sanford Records and Papers, 1945-1998
Duke University Archives
Board of Trustees Records, 1860-2004
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Accession A91-134, 1982-1989, (4) Boxes
  - Correspondence1982- (Box 1)
  - Charter and Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Minutes (Box 1)
  - Director's Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Private Adjudication Center, Inc.1982-1985 (Box 1)
  - Private Adjudication Foundation1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - PAF - Correspondence to Trustees1989 (Box 1)
  - PAF - Correspondence to Corporation1989 (Box 1)
  - PAC - Babcock Foundation1985-1989 (Box 1)
  - Z. Smith Reynolds1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - PAF - Individual Donors1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - PAC - Annual Report (Duplicates)1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - PAC - Information Booklet1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - UNR Claims Resolution Facility Manuals1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - PAC - Manville Correspondence1988 (Box 1)
  - PAC Grants1988 (Box 1)
  - Farm Loans1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - PAC - Farmer's Home Administration1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Middle District of North Carolina Rules Committee1984 (Box 1)
  - Federal Arbitration Rules Research Committee1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Unfoldered Materials - Minutes, Correspondence, etc.1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - Regions (Box 2)
    - Midwest Region Alumni (Box 2)
    - New England Alumni (Box 2)
    - New York Metro Alumni (Box 2)
    - Northeast Region Alumni (Box 2)
    - Alabama (Box 2)
    - Alaska (Box 2)
    - Alberta (Box 2)
    - Arizona (Box 2)
    - Arkansas (Box 2)
    - Belgium (Box 2)
    - Southern California (Box 2)
    - Western Justice Center (Box 2)
    - Northern California (Box 2)
    - Chicago (Box 2)
    - Colorado and Wyoming (Box 2)
    - Connecticut (Box 2)
    - Delaware (Box 2)
    - District of Columbia (Box 2)
    - Florida (Box 2)
    - Georgia (Box 2)
    - Hawaii (Box 2)
    - Idaho (Box 2)
    - Illinois (Box 2)
    - Indiana (Box 2)
    - Iowa (Box 2)
    - Japan (Kansai Region) (Box 2)
    - Southern Japan (Box 2)
    - Kansas (Box 2)
    - Korea (Box 2)
    - Kentucky (Box 2)
    - Louisiana (Box 2)
    - Los Angeles (Box 2)
    - Maritime Provinces (Box 2)
    - Maine (Box 2)
    - Maryland (Box 2)
    - Massachusetts (Box 2)
    - Western Michigan (Box 2)
    - Mideastern Region (Box 2)
    - Minnesota (Box 2)
    - Mississippi (Box 2)
    - Missouri (Box 2)
    - Montana (Box 2)
    - Nebraska (Box 2)
    - New Hampshire (Box 2)
    - Northern New Jersey (Box 2)
    - New Mexico (Box 2)
    - Western New York (Box 2)
    - Eastern New York (Box 2)
    - Southern New York (Box 2)
    - New Zealand (Box 2)
    - United Kingdom (Box 2)
    - Utah (Box 2)
    - Vermont (Box 2)
    - Virginia (Box 2)
    - West Virginia (Box 2)
    - Wisconsin (Box 2)
    - Wyoming (Box 2)
    - International (Box 2)
    - Washington (Box 2)
    - Eastern North Carolina (Box 2)
    - Middle District North Carolina (Box 2)
    - Western North Carolina (Box 2)
    - North Dakota (Box 2)
    - Southern Ohio (Box 2)
    - Central Ohio (Box 2)
    - Northern Ohio (Box 2)
    - Oklahoma (Box 2)
    - Ontario (Box 2)
    - Oregon (Box 2)
    - Western Pennsylvania (Box 2)
    - Eastern Pennsylvania (Box 2)
    - Rhode Island (Box 2)
    - South Carolina (Box 2)
    - South Dakota (Box 2)
    - Switzerland (Box 2)
    - Eastern Tennessee (Box 2)
    - Middle and Western Tennessee (Box 2)
    - West Texas (Box 2)
    - South Texas (Box 2)
    - North Texas (Box 2)
  - Pickett Road Building (Box 2)
  - Literature Regarding Other Centers (Box 2)
  - Meetings1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Lender-Borrower Program1988 (Box 3)
  - Accidents1985-1987 (Box 3)
  - Maritime1987-1988 (Box 3)
  - Finances1986-1988 (Box 3)
  - Fee Dispute Program1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Memorandac. 1983 (Box 3)
  - Research1985 (Box 3)
  - Exxon1990 (Box 3)
  - Report (Update) - Audit1988 (Box 3)
  - Fees1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Meeting Minutes, Reports Re: PAC Status / Future1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Rules1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Rosenberg Seminar in Dispute Resolution1985 (Box 3)
  - Business (Filings, Acceptances, Trials and Settlements)1988 (Box 3)
  - Future Plans1987-1988 (Box 3)
  - Foster, "Feasibility Study of Franchising for the Private Adjudication Center" paper1987 (Box 3)
  - Report on Review of Financial Statements1986 (Box 3)
  - IOLTA (Information on Lawyers' Trust Accounts)1988-19901984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence Re: Publications1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence Re: Donations1987-1989 (Box 3)
  - American Bar Association Retirement Plan Pamphlets (Box 3)
  - Macarthur Foundation Correspondence1988 (Box 3)
  - General Financial Correspondence1978-1984 (Box 3)
  - Hewlett Foundation Correspondence and 1987 Annual Report1987-1988 (Box 3)
  - Kellogg Foundation - Correspondence and Annual Report1988 (Box 3)
  - Lilly Endowment Correspondence1988 (Box 4)
  - IOLTA (Information on Lawyers' Trust Accounts)1988-19901988-1990 (Box 4)
  - IOLTA Grant1986 (Box 4)
  - NIDR (National Institute for Dispute Resolution)1983-1984 (Box 4)
  - NIDR Innovation Fund1988-1990 (Box 4)
  - Babcock Foundation (Box 4)
  - Fletcher Foundation1988 (Box 4)
  - Smith-Richardson Foundation1988 (Box 4)
  - Founders Campaign - NC Bar Association (Box 4)
  - Court Management Booklet - Johnson Foundation1980 (Box 4)
  - Smith-Richardson Grant - Clinical Course1987-1989 (Box 4)
  - Robert W. Woodruff Foundation1988 (Box 4)
  - Director's Correspondence1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee - Agendas and Memos1985-1989 (Box 4)
  - Budget, Audit - Correspondence and Reports1986-1987 (Box 4)
- Accession A93-71, 1983-1992, (2) Boxes
  - Clients' and Lawyers' Forum1988 (Box 5)
  - Toyota Correspondence1985-1989 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence RE: PAC Services1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - Reports and Financial1991 (Box 5)
  - Construction, CIDRS1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - Construction Correspondence1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - RAND - Arbitration Report1989 (Box 5)
  - Judges Correspondence1988-1990 (Box 5)
  - Credentials Committee1988 (Box 5)
  - McGovern, Francis - Correspondence1988 (Box 5)
  - Regional Representatives1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - PAC Information Booklets (Box 5)
  - Medical Malpractice Research Project Conference Booklet1989 (Box 5)
  - Minutes and Membership of Board1987-1989 (Box 5)
  - Private Adjudication Foundation List1989 (Box 5)
  - Grants and Financial1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - PDC Fundraising1990 (Box 5)
  - Financial Reports and Correspondence1992 (Box 5)
  - Articles of Incorporation1984-1985 (Box 5)
  - Grants and Financial1992 (Box 5)
  - Grants and Program Information1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - Board of Directors Correspondence1987-1992 (Box 5)
  - Annual Report1990-1991 (Box 6)
  - Pamphlet: Alternatives to the High Cost of Litigation1991 (Box 6)
  - Finance1984-1990 (Box 6)
  - State Justice Institute Booklet1992 (Box 6)
  - Program for Judges - Correspondence1991 (Box 6)
  - New Business1988-1989 (Box 6)
  - American Arbitration Association1989 (Box 6)
  - IOLTA Grant Accounting1991 (Box 6)
  - Metzloff - Concept Paper on ADR Strategies1991 (Box 6)
  - Insurers1988-1989 (Box 6)
  - PAC - Rationale for Support1987 (Box 6)
  - Dalkon Shield1988-1991 (Box 6)
  - Dalkon Shield1991 (Box 6)
  - Civil Rules Council1988-1989 (Box 6)
  - Teaching1988-1990 (Box 6)
  - State Justice Institute1988-1991 (Box 6)
  - American Law Institute (ALI) / American Bar Association (ABA) Program1983-1989 (Box 6)
  - ALI / ABA - Annual Report1989 (Box 6)
  - PAC Clinic1988 (Box 6)
  - Malpractice1989 (Box 6)
  - Malpractice Project1988-1989 (Box 6)
  - Clients and Lawyers Forum1988-1989 (Box 6)